<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sukhvir&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sukhvir&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>💡 Creating GPT2: My lessons learnt</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/creating_gpt2_my_lessons_learnt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/creating_gpt2_my_lessons_learnt/</guid>
      <description>My journey building GPT2, following Andrej Karpathy&amp;#39;s tutorials. My personal insights, challenges, and lessons learned - from data prep to distributed training. A candid look at creating a large language model and practical tips.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>🧠 Neural Networks and Backpropagation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/nn_and_backpropagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/nn_and_backpropagation/</guid>
      <description>Follow my journey along Andrej Karpathy&amp;#39;s YouTube series on AI/ML zero to hero training</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome 👋</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/welcome/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the blog</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/building_rag_applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/building_rag_applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the last year, I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a lot of time developing various AI use cases and applications within my organization. And I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot during this process. Majority of the applications that are built are around robotic process automation, feature extraction, and rag. Talking about rag, let&amp;rsquo;s focus on rag in this particular article. Here are some of the few lessons that I&amp;rsquo;ve learned. Here are the few things that I found interesting and just some general comments that I&amp;rsquo;d like to tell you all about. So firstly, something that I think we all know, something you must have already heard about but I just want to reinforce and stress that this is, I&amp;rsquo;ve not had a unique experience here and I&amp;rsquo;ll face the same problem that most do. 80%, I would say minimum is the amount of time you spend just cleaning up the data and make sure data is correct before you even get to any kind of AI process use case development and code development and application development. That takes a majority of time. In a RAG use case, for most organization, yes, there are multi-modal RAGs out there, there are fancy tools available that you can watch on YouTube, but for most organizations, you&amp;rsquo;re going for traditional data set which may include things like PowerPoints, Excels, DocX files, PDFs, these are what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for. The problem here is most of the content inside these files is generated for human beings to look at. Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s an office environment and that will be the case. But most content that is generated for human eyes is not necessarily designed for LLM consumption. Taking PowerPoints as an example, most of the PowerPoints are not text-heavy. They&amp;rsquo;re visuals-heavy. They&amp;rsquo;re infographics. There are also a lot of processes, process-centered operating procedures, policies and guidelines and related documents that most organizations have, they would like to put a rag chatbot on. They contain visual elements like infographics that may contain information within that graphic that is not necessarily reflected in the text of the document. In which case when you try to feed it to something like a large language model using and sort of parsing that data set, those that information will be lost. Only the text when you try to feed it to something like a large language model using and sort of parsing that data set, those, that information will be lost, only the text will be retained. We can certainly be, we can certainly lead to inferior products on the other end. The other thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve quite learned is that there is a lot of value in sort of communicating to the organization, not the organization, but to the business users within the organization about the non-deterministic and stochastic nature of the LLM. It&amp;rsquo;s important for them to understand that if they ask the same question five times, they will get five different answers. Of course, we can take a lot of measures to avoid hallucinations. I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about hallucinations as such but they would not get a deterministic answer every single time. This is kind of important especially in a chatbot sort of scenario to sort of explain to the users that this is a built-in feature of the system not a bug. Speaking of rag implementation itself I think when it comes to the ETL pipeline or the data loading pipeline for a rag use case as an example, the very first step that you do is you&amp;rsquo;re going to have to pass those documents. Like I said, there are four primary sets of documents that most organizations will be dealing with, PowerPoint, Excels, DocX files, and PDFs. So the first step is really to parse them and to extract all the content within it in a sort of structured way. Typically we use Markdown for this. We tried many, many different parsers. I think the best one that sort of does the job most reliably and most effectively and sort of respects where our data lives is Azure Document Intelligence. We have our data boundaries that is held between the Swiss data center within our known data center for the Azure environment, cloud environment that we have. Therefore we can put up to confidential data within this environment, which complies with our safety, with our classification policy and security policies. So given that, either we could use on-prem document process, or we could use a Cloud Service that&amp;rsquo;s hosted on Azure. Azure Document Intelligence seemed like the best of the class here. The other ones that we tried were dokling, and we also tried Magnum, I think it&amp;rsquo;s called. But I think overall document intelligence was the best in retaining the layout of the documents and also extracting all of the content from the document in a structured way in a mark down format. So this is the one that we decided to use. As I mentioned, obviously, the visual elements are kind of lost. But here now, lately, we started experimenting with using document intelligence to pass the content. And document intelligence naturally captures the fact that there are figures in a particular area, and it will mark down with a figure tag. Whenever that figure tag is detected, we literally carve after a figure and send it to GPT-4 or Vision Model to summarize what is being conveyed by the figure and put it inside the document itself. So we are starting to now look at Vision-enabled document intelligence to sort of capture all of the information of a given document within a markdown file as an output. So document intelligence has really been a winning factor here for us. Then comes chunking. Once you have your past documents, you need to chunk them in a meaningful way. And there are many, many, many chunking strategies out there. There is character splitting, recursive character splitting, the semantic splitting, many, many different ways to do the chunking and splitting. I think what I&amp;rsquo;ve found best especially for office related documents and policies and procedures, these are nicely structured for human eyes in a sort of report style format. There are headings and there are sections and each section contains a unit of information that is contained within that particular section. So for me, what I found best was to split or to chunk these past documents by section. So by using Markdown headers, H1, H2, H3 headers as a way to split these documents using Langchane&amp;rsquo;s Markdown header splitter as the chunking strategy here. Another thing I think was important during chunking process was to also include in the metadata of each chunk the source of the document, the URL, where the document was searched from, the title of the document, the headings as the metadata of a particular chunk, the page number the chunk came from within the source document. So those four things are included in the chunking process. Next thing that I guess a bit more advanced, RAG systems do is keyword generation because we can do the vector search and the retrieval using both the embeddings or the vector similarity, but also using keywords. So the next step that I do, or what we did for our RAG was to send our chunks to a GPT-4.0 model to generate five to six keywords that represent what is being conveyed in that particular chunk. This is also included in the metadata of a chunk. Once all of this is done, we&amp;rsquo;ve done the parsing of the document using document intelligence. We&amp;rsquo;ve done the chunking using the Markdown headers player. Chunking method, we generated some metadata, we generated some keywords for it. Then we vectorized it using a vector database. Here are some of the lessons learned. Also is the fact that if you are able to compartmentalize the vector database into different collections of different topics, that helps with retrieval as well. Putting everything up into a single bucket while it&amp;rsquo;s okay, I found the performance to be better by sort of containerizing, hey, this is&amp;ndash; these set of documents talk about travel-related policies. These set of documents talk about maternity leave related or travel or event-related policies and things like that. So you split it up by topic. So you can retrieve chunks and documents and objects from a particular topic based on a user&amp;rsquo;s question. If the user&amp;rsquo;s question is specific to a topic, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to retrieve irrelevant chunks or you don&amp;rsquo;t need to even search for irrelevant within irrelevant chunks from other topics. You only force in a particular topic. If a user&amp;rsquo;s question involves multiple topics, then you sort of query those multiple topics and retrieve relevant chunks for it. So by compartmentalizing the collections by topic, was a helpful strategy. Another thing for your ETL pipeline that is also good to make sure, especially in a corporate setting with these source documents, these policies may regularly get updated, so how do you ensure your rag chatbot reveals the right answer all the time is to also create a monitoring of the file sources that you have. So things like tracking file modifications, deletions, and additions. And be able to handle that. So if a file is modified or added, if the file is modified, find the chunks that you have in your vector database, destroy them, and treat it as if it&amp;rsquo;s a new file. So parse it, chunk it, and add it again. If a file is new file, do the same thing. If the file has been deleted, simply to remove all the chunks from your vector database. The way we decided to go by doing that was to maintain a state file, which sort of captured the files that have been processed. The previous ETL pipeline was run and any new files since then on a nightly basis is checked. Any new files since then I then just updates the state and then you take relevant actions accordingly. One perhaps another caution point here is where does your source data live? Do you read the golden source, or the golden copy of these files, or do you create a copy of these files, and work on those copies? How do you ensure the copies remain true to the golden source? All of these things considerations must be taken care of. We used SharePoint online folders as a repository to collect the data from for our ETL pipelines. But again, here in a corporate settings, especially in a Microsoft environment, people are starting to use SharePoint Online web pages and sites to store information and departmental policies and procedures in sort of web pages. These are dot ASP pages and perhaps building a connector to sort of fetch the data off of a particular page. Things like SharePoint on-prem, things like shared drives, all of these sources are valid and should be considered for onboarding into your rack pipeline. The other thing that we did for something else that we noticed during document intelligence while it does a really, really good job, sometimes, especially for our corporate template of Word documents, Excel documents and PowerPoint documents, we noticed that when document intelligence was sort of passing them, it did not identify all the headers correctly within the document. It identified our root header, our very first title of the document as an H1 header and then sort of put everything else, all the other content within that. It did not then identify H2 headers and H3 headers. This is a problem when you&amp;rsquo;re trying to chunk because your entire document becomes one chunk. This issue was done at random and perhaps it was linked to the corporate style of the documents that we have our own templates. Doing it on general word documents that don&amp;rsquo;t comply with our corporate template, this was never an issue, was only an issue. So there&amp;rsquo;s don&amp;rsquo;t comply with our corporate template. This was never an issue, was only an issue. So there&amp;rsquo;s something to do with our corporate template. But something like this might be of useful use of to you as well, and something for you to think about. Okay, moving on from chunking an ETL pipeline to the RAG process itself. So for example, we did a meeting services related at a rat chat pod, the meeting services department in an organization that tracks, that manages meetings, travels, event organization, meeting room bookings, catering, restaurant bookings, and all of these kind of stuff for different events and the meetings that we hold within our organization. And they have lots of policies and procedures around this and guidelines for users to book some of these services or to do some of these things. So as a rat chat bot, on top of the ETL that we built was, we would take a user&amp;rsquo;s question. And then the first thing that we do is we sort of classify the user&amp;rsquo;s question as to what topics is the user asking about. So we take the user&amp;rsquo;s question, send it to an LLM and with a prompt saying, user&amp;rsquo;s question must comply with one or many of these particular topics. If it&amp;rsquo;s outside those topics, then the user&amp;rsquo;s question is out of scope for this right chat box. Simply reply back to the user saying, we do not have relevant information for that particular question, please contact the meeting services team directly with your video inquiry. So if the user asks questions like, what is today&amp;rsquo;s weather? This is outside the scope of the RAC Chatbot, and they&amp;rsquo;ll get a standard stock standard reply. But otherwise, we&amp;rsquo;ll ask the LLM to categorize users&amp;rsquo; question into one or multiple topics that we have within our collection within our vector database. We&amp;rsquo;ll collect those topics and there&amp;rsquo;ll be a metadata field that will pass to the to our retriever so that it can retrieve from the from the right collection. The other thing that I also do with the user&amp;rsquo;s query is sort of rephrase that query. So if you have a memory built in where the user may ask, I want to&amp;ndash; what is the seating capacity of this particular room? And in the next question, they ask, oh, does that room support hybrid meetings? The LLM needs&amp;ndash; the RAG service needs to know what that is referring to, the word that, and the second question, what what that is referring to, the word that in the second question, what is that even referring to? So to be able to fill in that gap, it needs the history of messages that have been passed. So we need to reformulate users&amp;rsquo; question into a meaningful way so that the LLM can then respond. So we rephrase the query to take in previous queries. In context to fill and fill up all those gaps. Then what we do is we send, we create keywords for users query as well, and then we do, we generate embeddings for users question, and then we do sort of retrieval based on the embeddings and the keywords similarities search as well. We do BM25 retrieval here. Then we pass the retreat chunks. You can select how many, plus five, plus 10, and the user&amp;rsquo;s question to the LLM and pass all of that information to the LLM to generate a coherent answer. As per the RAG things, one of the things that we do provide back to the user as a response citations, the titles, the page numbers as well. Another thing we&amp;rsquo;ve recently added to our to our rag chat bot is a re-ranker and this has been game changer. We&amp;rsquo;ve been known while the LLM does a GPD 4.0 or less the LLM specifically does a really really good job with the jumbled sort of chunks that it is sent we sent top 10 but then not necessarily in the order that you would like some of the more sometimes sometimes irrelevant chunks are above good chunks are in the middle or at the bottom what a re-ranker is does is it does a really really good job in re-priizing and reorganizing chunks. So we&amp;rsquo;ve now started doing retrieving up to 30 or 40 chunks from the from the retriever, giving it to the re-ranker to pick out the top 10 and give those top 10 in a prioritized manner to the LLM. And you get a much better higher quality sort of response on the other end as a result of it as well. One thing I would also talk about is the&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cyber_attacks_on_llms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cyber_attacks_on_llms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of talk around cyber security of artificial intelligence and there are many many many examples and papers online where people are discussing the the cyber security implications of generative AI and large language models. A lot of the examples that I&amp;rsquo;m seeing online are things what I would call social engineering of a large language model, where there are a bunch of different examples of how we can trick the large language models to bypass the safety guardrails and respond to us in a particular manner such that it bypasses a guardrail. So show me how to create a ransomware. Most large language models of today will sort of deny that request saying this goes against their content policies or ethical obligations or safety guidelines that they have been put in place from the reinforced human learning and feedback RLHF or RHLF sort of life cycles and pipelines during the development and sort of creation of these large language models. But a lot of the examples online sort of talk about prompt engineering and sort of prompt injection as a way of getting the large language models to bypass those safety and guardrails and sort of reveal the malicious answer. This is great. This is good to see. But this is, I don&amp;rsquo;t know where the cybersecurity implication here is. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a risk in the sense that the large language models cannot be relied upon to maintain their safety guidelines, unintended way by subjecting it to certain precisely constructed prompts to get it to do that. I would like some examples where how this will actually apply in an organization that can be leveraged into a full-on attack scenario. How can this actually work? Because this seems like social engineering of a large language model to get it to do something based on some of the ways you are trying to influence it to do it. Are there any attacks on a large language model itself akin to an attack on a software library or an application that you download from the internet which might have inherent vulnerability that the attackers might exploit? Are there any cybersecurity attacks or papers out there or proven demonstrations that do that against any open source or foundational large language models because that would be very very interesting where i can see sort of prompt engineering coming into the foray is if i imagine a scenario like where we have uh security teams are relying upon a large language model to monitor telemetry of an organization and when there is a anomaly in the telemetry when something which means there&amp;rsquo;s something going on in the organization that is unpredictable, unpredicted or unforeseen or something that is out of the ordinary. Perhaps the large language model has been enabled to execute certain binaries to go and prevent or sort of prevent or remediate whatever is going on in the organization. So what we could do as an attacker would be to sort of create malicious activity within the organization, knowing full well that it will be detected, but the goal is to be detected, and sort of plant or replace the binary or a script that the large language model uses to deal with that kind of problem. So let&amp;rsquo;s say you attempt to create, you download a malicious binary onto a Windows device in your organization. This will certainly trigger Windows Defender alerts to, for example, Sentinel. And let&amp;rsquo;s say you have a large language model that&amp;rsquo;s monitoring Sentinel alerts, and it has a script that goes ahead and quarantines or deletes the malicious binary from a Windows device, for example. So as an attacker, you planted this binary into the Windows device with the full intention of it being detected and an alert being generated. At the same time, you replace that deletion binary that the LLM uses to clean up with your own malicious script. But you do not have the permissions to launch that script, or if you do have permissions, you don&amp;rsquo;t have enough sufficient permissions like the admin. You&amp;rsquo;re not privileged escalated to execute with the right amount of permissions. So by forcing a binary onto a Windows device, you&amp;rsquo;ve triggered an alert. The large language model sort of looks at the alert. Large language model then triggers, as part of its automated processes, that deletion binary and deletion binary is corrupted in a malicious binary that you planted, and thereby sort of using a large language model as a way of privilege escalating and running a particular script of your design but this is no different to typical attacks llms in this particular case are just like any other applications that are being used to to sort of execute other files so you&amp;rsquo;re using one using a privileged process to launch another process, thereby making sure that the secondary process that has been launched has the privileges of the first process. But are there any other examples of using large language models or exploiting large language models that go beyond prompt engineering of those large language models. If so, please feel free to comment and let me know about it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cyber_implications_of_onboarding_ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cyber_implications_of_onboarding_ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, we all know AI has taken the industry by a storm, and organizations are starting to rapidly pivot towards artificial intelligence and sort experimentation that&amp;rsquo;s happening within the organizations to try to keep up with the pace of AI and to sort of figure out where AI fits best within the workings of the inner organization. All of this experimentation is great and it should be encouraged. Taking my own organization as an example, we&amp;rsquo;ve gone absolutely toe deep into artificial intelligence. We&amp;rsquo;ve gone full tilt, and we&amp;rsquo;re trying to onboard it within the organization. We have several use cases that have been collected organically from the organization where people have come forward with ideas where AI could be of benefit. These range from robotic process automation using AI. A majority of the use cases are around RAG, retrieval augmented generation, and there are the use cases are around RAG, or retrieval augmented generation, and there are several use cases around this, including RAG chatbots. There are other use cases around text summarization, image generation, and things like that as well. And this is great to see, that we&amp;rsquo;re organically getting around 80 to 90 to 100 use cases in the organization, and that&amp;rsquo;s fantastic. What we&amp;rsquo;re also doing right now is actively sort of going through experimentations and trying out, different units are trying out different AI technologies. Taking RAC, for example, we have several sort of RAC frameworks that are being experimented on within the organization between different teams. Some people are going with Langflow and Langraph and sort of Langchain, and some others are going with things like Langsmith, and some of them are going with RACflow, and some units are creating their own sort of frameworks and tools as well. While this is excellent, this is great to see, especially in the early days of AI adoption and especially RAC technologies, we are sort of experimenting with different sort of frameworks and hopefully in some time in the future we can converge on a singular sort of framework strategy, platform strategy, moving forward so that we&amp;rsquo;re not reinventing the wheel and we&amp;rsquo;re sort of aligned on a singular way and we can all train on a similar set of technology. All of this is great. Where perhaps a little bit of a concern lies for me as a cybersecurity professional is that cybersecurity is a step behind in this process. Because of this unchecked experimentation, which is quite good and great to see organizations sort of doing this and embracing a technology so good, cybersecurity is unable to keep up with the pace of experimentation and proof of concepts that are being developed in the organization. And because there&amp;rsquo;s so many diverse set of technologies and frameworks that are being tried out, we can&amp;rsquo;t keep up with the pace of this development. So this is a potential vulnerability within the organization and something we need to especially keep an eye on. Experimentation should be encouraged and should be allowed, but it should be done in a safe and secure manner, perhaps in a sandbox environment. We need to think about what data we&amp;rsquo;re putting in, not giving it access to production system, not giving it access to production data, thinking about the privacy implications of data, thinking about what vulnerabilities you might be introducing as a result of a lot of these libraries and open source frameworks and libraries that we&amp;rsquo;re using to generate the code bases for our technologies. All of this can introduce vulnerabilities into the system and something to think about. Perhaps another area where cybersecurity or the information security teams are sort of a step behind in this process, we need to upskill our information security professionals as well on AI technologies. They&amp;rsquo;re very skilled and very professional with traditional computing technologies. They know how to defend and secure them. But when it comes to artificial intelligence, it is a black box like to many other people. But in cybersecurity, we need to know our enemy to better defend against them. So it&amp;rsquo;s important that we upskill our cybersecurity professionals on the art of AI, what is actually happening inside some of these popular use cases like RAG, what are the different elements, how they interact with each other, and knowing those interactions, those connections, help you envisage where the problems may lie and where the problems may come from in terms of adversaries and attacks and where to put your monitoring and tracing and all of that sort of stuff in place. So all in all to say that cybersecurity security is an important part of the conversation when it comes to onboarding artificial intelligence into the organization and must be must be thought of and taken care of. So while experimentation is great, let&amp;rsquo;s do so in a safe and a secure manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
